<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Historical reflections on the Bishop of Rome: chiefly discovering those events of humane affaires which most advanced the papal usurpation. By John Wagstaff, M.A. O.C.</title>
            <author>Wagstaffe, John, 1633-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1035_9</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863847</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863847</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116062</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96402)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116062)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1035[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Historical reflections on the Bishop of Rome: chiefly discovering those events of humane affaires which most advanced the papal usurpation. By John Wagstaff, M.A. O.C.</title>
                  <author>Wagstaffe, John, 1633-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Hen: Hall, for Ric. Davis; and are to be sold by S. Thompson at the Bishops Head in St Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final contents leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 1.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Primacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116062:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Hiſtorical Reflections</hi> ON THE BISHOP OF ROME: CHIEFLY DISCOVERING Thoſe Events of Humane Affaires which moſt advanced THE <hi>PAPAL <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RPATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN WAGSTAFF, <hi>M. A.</hi> O. C.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Hen: Hall,</hi> for <hi>Ric. Davis;</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>S. Thompſon</hi> at the Biſhops Head in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:116062:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116062:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> PRAEFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe <hi>Reflections</hi> having laine by me, long enough to coole the heat of my invention; upon a late review of them; I was embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to this Publication. And here I dare promiſe the Reader, that he ſhall not meet with <hi>Crambe bis cocta,</hi> or a meer garbling of other mens labours. For amongſt all the various Tracts written againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> there never came any into my hands of the ſame kind. Now if the novelty hereof ſhall invite any one to a peruſal, perhaps he will not altogether repent his pains; eſpecially if he intend for Hiſtorical Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg. In regard that this Treatiſe, may ſerve as a Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratour or Pointer out, of the moſt remarkable revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions in Eccleſiaſtique affairs, and the moſt notable jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of time.</p>
            <p>The thing which I chiefly aime at in the enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is, to make it appeare; <hi>That the Hierarchical Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of the Roman Church, was not extant in the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned times, when the old Roman Empire flouriſht: But was contrived in the daies of ignorance, between the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome, and the Leaders or Princes of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:116062:3"/>Nor would the truth of this aſſertion be in the leaſt manner doubted; were we not almoſt benighted with darke ignorance, in reference to preceeding ages. For as on the one hand; an infinite number of Books, have been partly aboliſhed, partly counterfeited, and Partly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterated or corrupted: So on the other hand; Thoſe Books which remaine entire, are for the moſt part written, either by unskilful or partial pens. However from the very preſent records, an unpraejudic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d man though of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary parts may gather; That the modern Policy which faſhions a great part of the world, as well in Church as State did take it's beginning, ſince the inundations of the Northerne People.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>July</hi> the <hi>20. 1660.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTCRIPT.</head>
            <p>I have not quoted any Authours, for theſe Paſſages which are reflected on, in the following Treatiſe. When I read the Hiſtorians, whence the foundation of my diſcourſe is gathered, it was not in my thoughts to make uſe of them this way. Afterwards reflecting on the ſeries of affairs in Chriſtendome, and framing ſeveral medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereupon: Though I very well remembred the Hiſtorians; yet I had forgot the names of many Hiſtorians whence I gathered it. Nevertheleſſe I can aſſure the Reader, that I have hardly mention'd any Hiſtorical paſſage, which is not very obvious, in one of theſe three Authours, <hi>Blondus, Baronius,</hi> and <hi>Platina.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116062:3"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> That the Roman Biſhops had no ſupremacy over the Primitive Chriſtians.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have often delighted to trace out in my mind, the footſteps of the papal uſurpations. And perhaps it will pleaſe the <hi>Reader,</hi> to give him in one view, the ſeveral ſteps or degrees, by which the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop roſe unto ſuch a heigth; as to trample upon the necks, not only of his fellow Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, but alſo of Kings and Emperours themſelves. For that the <hi>Pope</hi> did not from the beginning enjoy, his preſent great and Lordly power, but arrived unto it by ſeveral gradations, in a long proceſſe of time; none but thoſe who are either wholy ignorant of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, or elſe ſwayed with invincible prejudice can offer to deny. It being manifeſt on all hands, that in the Primitive times, the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops were not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116062:4"/>taken notice of, as ſuperiours to all others; much leſſe as ſole Vicars under <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and infallible dictatours of Divine truth. Indeed you may meet in the ancient Authours, with commendations given unto the faith, profeſſed by the Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi> Which is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to him that conſiders, how pious at firſt they were in their lives, how glorious in their deaths, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring witneſſe to the Truth under Perſecution. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, when the whole Chriſtian world was under one Empire, and <hi>Rome</hi> the Metropolis or Emperial Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; It was but rational, that the new and riſing ſect of the Chriſtians, ſhould beſtow the notabl'ſt men of their party in that place. Hence it came to paſſe, that the <hi>Fathers</hi> dwelling in the Provinces, when they conteſted with <hi>Hereticks,</hi> did often commend the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith: as it were upbraiding their Antagoniſts, with a departure from thoſe, who reſided in the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis of the Empire, where uſually Learning and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doe moſt flouriſh.</p>
               <p>And to ſpeak the truth; That advantage which the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops had, by dwelling in the Emperial Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, was the chiefe temptation, at firſt inducing them to affect a ſupremacy. For that the dignity and grandeur of a City, or place of reſidence, was wont to put ſpirits into the Biſhops reſiding therein, <hi>Rome</hi> is not the onely example. So did <hi>Alexandria</hi> puffe up her Biſhops. So did <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Hers. So eſpecially did <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> make <hi>John the Conſtantinopolitan</hi> ſwell with ambition and pride, affecting the title of Oecumeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Biſhop. Nay, which you'l more wonder at, even ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116062:4"/>did <hi>Ravenna,</hi> when proud with <hi>Exarchs,</hi> animate her Biſhop alſo, in contending with the <hi>Roman</hi> for ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority. Which contention went ſo far, that the Church of <hi>Ravenna</hi> by reaſon of her ſeparation from <hi>Rome,</hi> was commonly called <hi>Allocephalis.</hi> Now by how much the renowned and ancient <hi>Rome,</hi> was more venerable in the eyes of men, than other Cities; by ſo much had the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops a fairer opportunity than others, to put themſelves forward, and uſurp an unlawfull power. Nor needed they to be minded of this advantage: ſuch of them as were of haughty ſpirits, beginning betimes to make uſe of it; amongſt whom I may juſtly reckon <hi>Leo</hi> ſurnamed <hi>the Great.</hi> For he and ſeverall others did take all occaſions to ſend pragmaticall letters, up and down the world about e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very important buſineſſe, which happened in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe let no one be afraid of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops, and be ready to aſcribe unto them an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Dioceſſe, when he finds them frequently ſending ſtately letters, to the Biſhops throughout the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world. Many of thoſe letters recorded in the book, entitled <hi>Epiſtolae decretales ſummorum Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> are falſe and counterfeit; many adulterated or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted; and many if true, are ſo haughtily written, as to argue the Authours pride, but not his power. For in the pimitive times, the Chriſtian Biſhops did gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally (and not only the <hi>Roman</hi>) write often to their fellow Biſhops, in whatſoever place they reſided. And this they did whether they had any power one over the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116062:5"/>other or no, meerly from a Principle of love or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity. Which familiar epiſtolary entercourſe with one another, was in thoſe daies laudable, and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt neceſſary: In regard the whole Chriſtian world was at that time under one Empire. Conſequently they were obliged, to exhort and admoniſh one another, upon a twofold reſpect. Partly grounded on that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, which members of the ſame Commonwealth, eſpecially thoſe of the ſame rank have with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And partly grounded on that ſpiritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, which ought to be between believers, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe of the ſame calling.</p>
               <p>But alas, had the world been perſwaded in the primitive times, that the letters of the <hi>Roman</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop were not onely charitative adviſoes; but dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torian mandates neceſſary to be obeyed: As procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forſooth from one, whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> had appointed head of his Church, and an oracle whence nothing but veritable anſwers ſhould be heard. I ſay, had ſuch a perſwaſion poſſeſſed the minds of men; They would have made it the common ſubject of their praiſes and thankſgiving. Without queſtion many Panegyricall orations, and many homilies would have been made, upon no other theme or text, than the praiſes of the <hi>Roman See,</hi> 
                  <q>and thanks unto God, for beſtowing on the Chriſtians, a viſible unerring decider of controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</q> Whereas on the contrary, if we peruſe the ancient Writers, we ſhall plainly perceive; how little the noiſe was, which the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops did make in their daies: So little that I much wonder they were no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116062:5"/>more talkt of, conſidering (as I ſaid before) their reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Metropol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and their virtues emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in the firſt Biſhops <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not the <hi>Fathers</hi> been very malignant in this caſe, (if the papal pretenſes were true) not to leave it ſet down expreſly in any of their writings, That <hi>Chriſt made Peter the head of his Church, and gave unto him an infallible ſpirit:</hi> As alſo that <hi>Peter being Biſhop of Rome, The following Biſhops in that City ſucceeded, him not only in his Biſhoprick; but likewiſe in his great priviledges of headſhip and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility.</hi> Moreover, did not the Fathers trouble themſelves to no purpoſe in toyling to make laborious confutations of hereticks, if they might have had preſent recourſe to a viſible unerring authority, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of controverſies. So that ſuppoſe the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks had refuſed to ſubmit unto this authority; The maine worke ſhould have been not to confute their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, but to convince them of the duty of their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſupreme judg.</p>
               <p>For my own part I verily believe, that if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> had been acknowledged in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, to be what he pretends to in theſe daies; The eyes of all nations would have been upon, that <hi>ſee;</hi> to revere it, to honour it, to bow down before it in the ſubmiſſion of their underſtandings. Nay further, I am really perſwaded; Had <hi>Chriſt</hi> intended ſuch a ſupreme power in his Church: Seeing it doth ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly import the Church's welfare to be generally known; We ſhould have had it ſet down in Scripture, with as expreſſe termes, as we find Juſtification by faith, or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116062:6"/>the reſurrection of the dead. But now on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, what is there left by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Penmen,</hi> which may be ſaid to patronize, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and infallibility of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> As for <hi>Peter;</hi> how eaſy were it for me, to evacuate thoſe trivial arguments, which are drawn from Scripture concerning him? which I forbeare to doe, becauſe it is not my intent, to inſiſt upon Logical arguments either <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con;</hi> but only to reflect on Hiſtorical paſſages.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I cannot chuſe but take notice, that when <hi>Peter</hi> came to <hi>Antioch;</hi> he walked not according to the truth; but was guilty of a great ſcandall, and thereupon withſtood to the face by <hi>Paul.</hi> Who makes it his buſineſſe in the two firſt Chapters to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> to prove himſelfe equall with the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> Nay when <hi>Peter</hi> (to ſpeak according to their own phraſe) was in <hi>Cathedra;</hi> in the midſt of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and other brethren: The definitive ſentence to which all did aſſent, proceeded from the mouth of <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, you muſt not look to have any hint of him in Scripture. <hi>Peter</hi> never being taken notice of, under ſuch a capacity: Nay, <hi>Paul</hi> in thoſe ſeveral <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> which he wrote either to or from <hi>Rome,</hi> doth not ſo much as mention <hi>Peter.</hi> Which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtrange, if <hi>Peter</hi> did dwell in that City. For <hi>Paul</hi> is ſolicitous, in mentioning ſeverall others farre leſſe conſiderable; whom he doth either ſalute, or ſend ſalutations from to others. But what if it ſhould be granted that <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome?</hi> I am confident it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116062:6"/>would trouble the whole <hi>Papacy,</hi> to prove that ever he was Biſhop of that City. <hi>Paul</hi> it's certain was there, and thoſe who contend that <hi>Peter</hi> was too, doe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally hold, they were both martired at the ſame time, the one by the Sword, the other by the Croſſe. Why then was <hi>Peter</hi> Biſhop, and not <hi>Paul?</hi> I'me ſure the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>Paul</hi> was entruſted with the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of the Uncircumciſion, as <hi>Peter</hi> with that of the Circumciſion: Nay <hi>James,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> did ſolemnly give the right hands of fellowſhip, unto <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> and <hi>Paul;</hi> That they ſhould goe to the Gentiles, and themſelves unto thoſe of the Circumciſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116062:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> How or by what cauſes the Pope was advanced to a ſupremacy in the Church.</head>
               <p>BUt I ſhall not trouble my ſelfe any longer, to make it appeare; that neither <hi>Peter,</hi> nor the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> had that power, which the later Biſhops pretend to derive from them: There being few in our Nation, that will gainſay the truth of what I have ſaid. Wherefore having allready made, ſuch briefe remarques, as plainly evince the <hi>Pope</hi> to be an uſurper: I am now come to what I did chiefely intend, namely to lay down the ſeveral ſteps or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, by which he was advanc'd in his uſurpations. This I ſhall doe by reflecting on the events of humane affairs, and giving an account in order, of the ſeveral cauſes; which did cooperate towards the bringing of the intolerable <hi>Roman</hi> yoake, on the necks of our <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt Cauſe therefore was, <hi>The removing of the Empertal ſeat by Conſtantine.</hi> For though a good while after him, there were Weſterne as well as Eaſtern Emperours. yet after the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on <hi>Italy,</hi> by the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruls</hi> firſt, and then the <hi>Goths;</hi> The Emperial Majeſty did entirely reſide at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> Now this City
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116062:7"/>by <hi>Conſtantines</hi> means, was grown ſo magnificent and auguſt, that it was dearer to the Emperours, than <hi>Rome</hi> in ſelfe. Inſomuch that when <hi>Belliſarius</hi> and <hi>Narſes,</hi> had recovered <hi>Italy</hi> from the <hi>Goths;</hi> The Emperours never affected, to goe and reſide at old <hi>Rome,</hi> by which means the Biſhop thereof, gained the more elbow rome to play <hi>REX.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>The reſiding of the Italian exarchs at Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venna. Juſtine</hi> the ſecond was Authour of the <hi>Exar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy;</hi> to which kind of government the <hi>Italian</hi> writers impute, moſt of the calamities afterwards befalling <hi>Italy.</hi> But indeed it was the occaſion of an other guiſe calamity, than they were aware of. For now neither the Emperour himſelfe, nor ſo much as his <hi>Exarch</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided at <hi>Rome:</hi> only a petty companion, who was ſent by the <hi>Exarchs</hi> to praeſide over the City; and was called <hi>Duke,</hi> in the ſame manner as the governour of <hi>Narni, Spoleto,</hi> and other townes of Italy. Hence it came to paſſe, that the ſplendour of Emperiall Majeſty being far removed, from the eyes of the <hi>Roman</hi> people: Their Biſhops ſhone ſo much the brighter, and gaind a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable increaſe of veneration.</p>
               <p>Thirdly; <hi>The comming of the Lombards into Italy;</hi> who intending the finall conqueſt of that Country for themſelves; made it their buſineſſe to deſtroy the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Emperour, whom they found Lord thereof. Wherefore as ſoone as the Emperour began to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe, the Inſolency of any Roman Biſhop, (who now by reaſon of the aforementioned cauſes began to play tricks) The <hi>Lombard</hi> was at hand to help him. Again
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116062:8"/>on the otherſide, when the <hi>Lombard</hi> out of a deſire to. win <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, fell foule with it's Biſhop; The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour for fear of looſing his dominion, was faine to helpe him, whom before he did endeavour to puniſh Marke how capriciouſly things in thoſe daies ſtood, and how exceeding well they ſuited with the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop Whenſoever he had to doe with the <hi>Lombard,</hi> he was ſure of the Emperous help; And when he contended with his Maſter, the Barbarian preſently took his part. Thus did he rivet himſelfe into his Authority, between the <hi>Emperour</hi> and the <hi>Lombard;</hi> till at laſt by the helpe of the <hi>French,</hi> He brought them both below himſelfe, as to any <hi>Italian</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>Fourthly; <hi>The reputation of Gregory, the firſt Roman Biſhop of that name, who was ſir named the Great.</hi> This man lived in the hotteſt ſeaſon of the Barbarian vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, when the Empire of the <hi>Romans</hi> and their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning failed. In ſuch an age as that was; he being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with great natural parts, and well accompliſht with acquired perfections, did eaſily overtop his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries. Before he was Biſhop; By his retiring for devotion's ſake to the private life of a Monk; By his zealous turning his own houſe at <hi>Rome</hi> into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery; In general, by his outward auſterity and ſanctity of life, he ſo gained upon the <hi>Roman</hi> people; that they would not part with him, when he proffered to goe into <hi>Brittany,</hi> for to convert the <hi>Saxons.</hi> And when he was ſent to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> upon publique em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, he quickly obtained the Emperour's favour.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116062:8"/>Afterwards when he was choſen Biſhop; By his zeale in continuing to write volume upon volume concerning the Chriſtian Doctrine; As alſo in deſtroying the Heathen Authours, and thoſe goodly buildings at <hi>Rome,</hi> which he feared might tempt the admiring be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders to hanker after the ancient <hi>Roman</hi> glory; By his new modelling the Chriſtian worſhip, adding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inventions of his own, to make it more ſplendid and pompous in vulgar eyes; By his converting the <hi>Engliſh Saxons;</hi> By theſe and many other waies he grew renowned in the world, and filled Chriſtendome with his name. Nor did his glory expire with his life; About an hundred years after this <hi>Gregory,</hi> our <hi>Bede</hi> in the Weſt, and <hi>Monke Damaſcene</hi> in the Eaſt, were paſſionate in their reſpects for him, and highly magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him in their writings. Nay generally the <hi>Monks</hi> for a long time, did ſo reverence his memory that he ſeemed to eclipſe the primitive <hi>Fathers.</hi> Now this great eſteem and high valuation which the world had of <hi>Gregory the firſt,</hi> did redound upon the <hi>Roman See,</hi> and proved notably advantageous for his ſucceſſours. But nothing more ſtrengthned their hands, than his converting our <hi>Engliſh Nation.</hi> No people in the world for a long time after were more prodigal of their bloud, more enpenſive of their eſtates, in behalfe of the <hi>Roman Biſhops,</hi> than our <hi>Engliſh:</hi> No people more earneſt in their devotion to <hi>Rome.</hi> This can be attributed to nothing elſe, but their converſion by <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> and to that impreſſion which his memory had left in the minds of their Anceſtours, and was handed along
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116062:9"/>from father to ſonne. Nay what ſay ye, if at this very day; the Gregorian praiſes be freſh amongſt our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Papiſts, who alſo have a tender regard for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of their Convertor <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and love the very <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictines</hi> for his ſake?</p>
               <p>Fifthly; <hi>The prodigious growth of the Saracenical Empire, founded by Mahomet in the time of Heracltus.</hi> The <hi>Saracens</hi> cut out ſo much worke, for the Graecian Emperour in his Eaſterne provinces that he was forced to neglect, and at laſt give over his intereſt in the Weſt. Now this may be obſerved all along in Hiſtory; that the weakning of the Emperours, was the ſtrengthning of the Popes.</p>
               <p>Sixthly; <hi>The general deluge of Barbarians, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelming the Romans in the Weſt, much about the ſame time that the Saracens did in the Eaſt. Pannonia, Italie, Spaine, France, Brittain,</hi> were all over-run not many years after one another. Theſe <hi>Barbarians</hi> comming from <hi>Climates,</hi> frozen with ignorance as well as cold, did both give and receive, a Conqueſt. As they Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the <hi>Romans,</hi> by their Sword: So they were reciprocally foild by the <hi>Roman</hi> Learning and Religion. Now the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the grand inſtrument of their converſion. For in thoſe times of general deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, he beſt held his own; and was moſt eminent in the eyes of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> by reaſon of his reſidence in that Renowned City; concerning which, before their paſſage over the <hi>Rhine</hi> and the <hi>Danow,</hi> they had heard their Fathers ſpeak of old. How feaſable then was it, for him to foiſt what he pleaſ'd into the beliefe of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116062:9"/>thoſe men, who newly came from worſhipping ſuch kind of Gods, as <hi>Aegypt</hi> was wont to adore? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las thoſe ſilly ſoules, taken up with amazement at a diſcovery of the true God, had neither leaſure nor abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to attend, the obſerving of thoſe obtruded foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which they did imbibe together with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of their Religion: Wherefore if he that firſt told them, of an omnipotent eternal God, whoſe ſeat was in the higheſt Heavens; and of a Crucified Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, did at the ſame time tell them of a S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> and his Succeſſour; Tis no wonder that they believed one, as well as the other. If <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour be an <hi>Arrian,</hi> then all thoſe whom he converts will be <hi>Arrians</hi> too. For it is well known; that the <hi>Viſigoths</hi> flying from before the approaching Hun, when they had obtained their requeſt from <hi>Valens,</hi> for a quiet Habitation in <hi>Thrace,</hi> did not only receive from him the Doctrine of Chriſt, but that of <hi>Arrius</hi> alſo: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they and their poſterity for a long time after, did ſtoutly maintain <hi>Arrianiſm.</hi> So great a prevalency hath that Doctrine, which is firſt ſeated in the ſpirits of men. Here I ſhall crave leave of the reader, to make a ſmall digreſſion concerning <hi>Baronius,</hi> with a promiſe to trouble him ſo no more. <hi>Baronius</hi> in his annals will needs have it, contrary to ſeveral Hiſtorians; that theſe <hi>Goths</hi> were converted to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, long before the time of <hi>Valens.</hi> His reaſon is, becauſe in the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> they had a Biſhop named <hi>Theophilus,</hi> preſent at the <hi>Nicene Councel.</hi> But I ſuppoſe nothing can be lawfully concluded thence,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116062:10"/>excepting this; that ſome few of them were Chriſtians in the dayes of <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> For my part, that the body of their nation was converted, before their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into <hi>Thrace,</hi> by the permiſſion of <hi>Valens,</hi> I ſee no reaſon to believe.</p>
               <p>Seventhly; <hi>The Colluſion between Zacharias the third, and Pipin Major domo to the King of France, Pipin</hi> made uſe of <hi>Zacharias's</hi> authority, towards the deciſion of that ridiculous queſtion; which was ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſent to <hi>Rome.</hi> Namely; <hi>Whether he that had the name and title of a King only, being given to idleneſſe: or he that was active and exerciſed the office and power of a King, deſerved to weare the regal diademe?</hi> Which in plain termes was this; Whether <hi>Chilperick</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> deſcended from the ancient race of Kings, having out of reſpect to his own eaſe, entruſted the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of affairs with his ſervant <hi>Pipin;</hi> might not be turned out of that throne, which his anceſtours had ſo long enjoyed, by his own ſervant, whom he had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly raiſ'd, to a Capacity of doing it if he would? The good Pope was not aſhamed of this ſenſeleſſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, nor needed he to be inſtructed, how profitable it was to judge for the ſtrongeſt: At length it came to this, that King <hi>Chilperick's</hi> head was ſhaven, and his man <hi>Pipin's</hi> wore the Crown. Now <hi>Pipin</hi> having made uſe of pontificial authority to cheat the poore <hi>Francks</hi> of their King, and to invade the temporal Soveraignty, did out of gratitude recompenſe the <hi>Pope,</hi> with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual juriſdiction over the <hi>Gallicane Church.</hi> Nay further, when <hi>Deſiderius</hi> the Lombard infeſted <hi>Gregory</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:116062:10"/>the third, <hi>Pipin</hi> out of a tender regard to that <hi>See,</hi> which had been ſo friendly towards him; not only by his aid delivered the <hi>Pope,</hi> from feare of being beſieged in <hi>Rome,</hi> but gave him as the <hi>Italian</hi> writers ſay, the <hi>Exarchate</hi> with ſeveral other territories.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, <hi>The Conquering arms of Charlemaign ſon to King Pipin;</hi> who having the ſame reaſons that his Father had, to indulge the <hi>pontificial See,</hi> confirmed whatſoever his Father <hi>Pipin</hi> had granted to the <hi>Pope.</hi> Yet to make him the more ſure, <hi>Leo the third</hi> with the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> elected him <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour. Hence it came to paſſe, that as far as the Conqueſts made by <hi>Charlemaigne</hi> did reach; So farre alſo did <hi>Papal</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority extend: No otherwiſe than the <hi>Mahometan</hi> doctrine, did enlarge it's bounds, by the victorious arms of <hi>Ottoman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have we proceeded, to the <hi>Pope's</hi> Eccleſiaſtique ſupremacy, through eight ſeverall cauſes. Of which the ſix former, may be accounted the more remote or procatarctique; The two latter being thoſe, which put together, doe integrate the principal efficient and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daequate cauſe. For although the ſix procatarctiques, did very much embroile the Church affairs, and laid them in a tendency to <hi>Papal</hi> encroachments: yet it is evident that the univerſal power, which the <hi>Pope</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired over the Weſtern Churches, owed it's very riſe and being, to the notorious jugling between the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops, and the uſurpers of the <hi>French Merovingean</hi> Crown. Well therefore may the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> be ſtiled the eldeſt ſons of the <hi>Papal</hi> Church: Nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116062:11"/>let them be ſtiled fathers thereof. There being no appearance in Hiſtory, of a generall ſubmiſſion unto the <hi>pontificiall See;</hi> untill the dayes of the traitor <hi>Pipin,</hi> and the Emperour his Son. But then you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, as it were a bargain ſtroake of mutual aſſiſtance, between the <hi>pontificial</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> tyrants. The <hi>pontificial</hi> aſſiſtance, is made uſe of by <hi>Pipin,</hi> for the depoſing his maſter, and invading the French Crown: By <hi>Charles</hi> his Sonne, for the obtaining of the Weſtern Empire. They on the other ſide, in lieu of their ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Kingdomes, ſettle upon the <hi>Popes</hi> an Eccleſiaſtique Soveraignty. Nor are they content to gratifie them only ſo, but they muſt needs be giving them a very fair temporal demeans. The taſt of which did ſo pleaſe their palates, that they have been ever ſince hankering, to be Lords paramount over all the world, in Civil as well as Eccleſiaſtical affairs. Wherefore it behoves me next to ſet down, the remaining cauſes of the <hi>Papal</hi> encroachment; Whereby the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was encouraged, to uſurp unto himſelfe the rights of the Magiſtrate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116062:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> How or by what Cauſes the Pope was not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in his Eccleſiaſtical uſurpation, but was alſo encouraged to invade the rights of the Magiſtrate.</head>
               <p>HEre I ſhall in the firſt place premiſe, that the cauſes mention'd in the foregoing Chapter, did not only advance the <hi>Pope's</hi> Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique Tyrannie; but alſo had an influence upon the making of way, for his temporal uſurpation. Had he not firſt come to that heighth in the <hi>Church,</hi> he could never have dreamt of a ſuperintendency over the <hi>ſtate.</hi> Likewiſe the cauſes which now follow, are to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed an influence upon the <hi>Popes</hi> domination ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, by way of confirming him in his unjuſt acqueſts Although I confeſſe they do more neerly concerne his invading the rights of the Magiſtrate, in regard that we have already brought him unto the higheſt pinnacle in the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ninthly; <hi>The donation which</hi> Pipin <hi>made, and his ſonne</hi> Charles <hi>confirmed unto the Pope;</hi> whereby he was poſſeſſed of a very large territory: yet not as Lord in chiefe thereof, but rather as a dependant on the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as appeares by ſeveral actions of <hi>Charlemaigne,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116062:12"/>and his Sons after him; which ſufficiently evince, that they kept the Soveraignty of thoſe places ſtill unto themſelves; however this proved ſuch a bait of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, to the <hi>Pope,</hi> that he hath ever ſince had an unbridled luſt, after the kingdomes of this world, and the glory thereof: inſomuch, that he who pretends to be the <hi>Univerſal Vicar of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Deputy</hi> to Him in His Kingdome, ſeems unto me a pretty riddle. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> doth abſolutely Declare, that His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is not of this world: But I pray to what world doth that belong, which is full of armed Souldiers, walled Cities, fortified Havens, ſtrong Gallies, great Guns, abundance of Ammunition and Treaſures.</p>
               <p>Tenthly; <hi>The general decay of Learning, after the dayes of</hi> Charlemaign: Whence it came to paſſe, that the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and the <hi>Weſt,</hi> were not more alienated one from the other, by the diſtinction of different Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, than they were, by the want of mutual corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence in learned entercourſes. Nay it was the policy of the <hi>Popes,</hi> by affronts done to the Emperours, and ſeveral other waies, to augment the ſtrangeneſſe between the <hi>Greeks</hi> and the <hi>Latines.</hi> That ſo the <hi>Barbarians</hi> being brought up in a prejudice, againſt the <hi>Gracians;</hi> might neglect their language, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently be overcaſt with ſuch a night of ignorance, that they ſhould not be able to ſee the injuſtice of the <hi>Papal</hi> proceedings. And truly to the loſſe of the <hi>Greek</hi> tongue, may juſtly be imputed the loſſe of all purity in the <hi>Latine;</hi> and conſequently of <hi>Hiſtory, Geography,</hi> skill in <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and whatſoever ſavour'd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116062:12"/>of polite learning. Thus the whole Weſtern Empire were quite deprived of the benefit they might have received, by informing their judgments in Religion, with the goodly books that were written in <hi>Greek:</hi> Nay they did not ſo much as knowingly converſe, with the <hi>Latin Fathers:</hi> So that it was allmoſt impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them, to be acquainted with the infant purity of the Chriſtian religion, which they had taken upon truſt from the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop. Whereas if they had but well ſtudied, the writings of thoſe men, whoſe Fathers were converted together with, nay ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> it would have been mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that he was no ſuch man amongſt the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as he pretended himſelfe to be amongſt them: As alſo how notoriouſly for the advancing of his own power, he had impoſ'd upon the credulous ignorance of their Heathen ſouls. Now that this tenth reaſon of the <hi>Papal</hi> encroachment, is not a bare notion, or a thing meerly bred in my own private conceptions, any one will confeſſe; who doth but conſider, how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally it is exemplified in the ſeries of humane tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. As long as this fog of ignorance, did darken mens underſtandings; neither the preaching, nor the martyrdome of thouſands of people, could much prevaile to the ſhaking off the <hi>Roman</hi> yoke. But the caſe was quite alter'd, when at the taking of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> the <hi>Graecian</hi> ſchollars were forced to ſly for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge among the Weſtern Chriſtians; they every where teaching their own tongue; the reviving of that noble language, did bring along with it, the reſtoration
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116062:13"/>of all Learning. So that now what neither <hi>Wicklef,</hi> nor <hi>Hus,</hi> nor <hi>Hierome of Prague,</hi> nor the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> and <hi>Albigenſes</hi> could effect, that <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> have wonderfully perform'd, to the Converſion of whole Nations. As ſoon as the reſtoration of learning had enlightned the world, men were of their own accord diſpoſd to follow any: who by breaking the ice as it were, ſhould lead the way to their ſpiritual free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, <hi>The fatal diſcord between the grand children of Charles the Great;</hi> who as ſoon as their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lewis</hi> the Godly was dead, fell together by the cares about the Empire. At laſt they came to this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that <hi>Lewis</hi> ſhould be King of <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſo much of <hi>France,</hi> as lieth betwixt the <hi>Meuſe</hi> and the <hi>Rhine. Charles</hi> ſhould be King of the reſt of <hi>France,</hi> except the Province of <hi>Narbone:</hi> which together with <hi>Italy,</hi> and the title of Emperour fell to <hi>Lotharius;</hi> who indeed ought to have been Emperour of the whole, as being the eldeſt, and choſen by their Father in his life time, to be his Colleague in the Empire: Thus was the Empire of <hi>Charlemaign</hi> cantonized by his Nephews, and at laſt brought to a contemptible ſtate, for want of eſtabliſhing a firme ſucceſſion in the Eldeſt. Hence it came to paſſe, that the <hi>Huns,</hi> the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and the <hi>Lombard Dukes,</hi> did miſerably afflict the Empire, finding no united ſtrength to oppoſe them. Moreover <hi>France</hi> fell quite off from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, being Governed by its own Kings. Nay when <hi>Otho the great,</hi> had ſetled the confuſions brought upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116062:13"/>
                  <hi>Italy,</hi> by <hi>Berengarius Guido</hi> and <hi>Lambert.</hi> Yet ſtill did the old danger hang over the Empire, for want of a firme Succeſſion: For as ſoon as he and his Son <hi>Otho the ſecond</hi> were dead; There grew that quarrel between ſome of the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Germans,</hi> about election of a new Empirour, which made way for the <hi>Pope</hi> to order all things, according to his own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, as appeares by the twelth cauſe that next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
               <p>Twelfthly, <hi>The formal making of the Empire ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, by the conſtitution of</hi> Otho <hi>the third, and</hi> Gregory <hi>the fifth;</hi> whereby the <hi>Romans</hi> were excluded from the chuſing of their own Emperour; It being wholy conferred on the <hi>Germane</hi> Princes. <hi>Otho</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> were induced to make this alteration, by ſome affronts which they had received from the <hi>Roman</hi> people. For <hi>Otho</hi> after the death of his Father, had like to have miſſed of the Emperiall Crown. The party of one <hi>Creſcentius</hi> a powerfull Roman, publickly giving out, that it was high time for the <hi>Italians,</hi> to chooſe themſelves an Emperour, and to bring the ſeat of the Empire into <hi>Italy</hi> again. However <hi>Otho</hi> at laſt carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and <hi>Creſcentius</hi> with his party did ſubmit. But when <hi>Otho</hi> had made, his own Countryman and kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Bruno Pope,</hi> by the name of <hi>Gregory the fifth,</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> brake out into greater diſcontents than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, ſo that the new made <hi>Pope</hi> is faine to fly for't. In his abſence the people of <hi>Rome</hi> make <hi>Creſcentius</hi> their Conſul, and he makes <hi>John Biſhop of Placenti a Pope.</hi> Well, the Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> marches into <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116062:14"/>takes the Caſtle of St <hi>Angelo</hi> in which <hi>Creſcentius</hi> had fortified himſelfe, and puts him to an ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous death. And having cruelly tortured <hi>John of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia,</hi> he reſettles his Cozen <hi>Pope Gregory.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he and his Cozen having been equally vext by the <hi>Roman</hi> people, did take a ſharpe revenge, in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring from them, upon their own nation, the power of chooſing the Emperour. <hi>Otho</hi> had no children to care for, and ſo was the more deſirous to have the Empire ſetled in an Elective way; after ſuch a manner as he thought was advantagious to the <hi>Germans.</hi> The cunning <hi>Pope,</hi> did not only gratifie his Countrimen, the <hi>Germans;</hi> and revenge himſelfe upon his enemies the <hi>Italians;</hi> but alſo abundantly provide for the emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lument of his ſucceſſours. It being provided in this conſtitution, that he who was Elected by the <hi>German Princes,</hi> ſhould be called <hi>Caeſar</hi> or <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Romans;</hi> but not <hi>Emperour</hi> or <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> till he was crowned and conſecrated by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Thus was the unreaſonabl'ſt thing in the world committed; that a Biſhop ſhould take from a People, over whom he had but the ſpiritual charge, their temporal birthright of Electing their own <hi>Prince,</hi> and conveigh much of it into his own hands. But when was this done? Even in that barbarous age, which was wrapt up in the very midnight of ignorance; which brought not forth, ſo much as one Eccleſiaſtique writer either good or bad. And therefore is noted for a miſerable age, by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe in the Column of his Chronology over againſt thoſe times, which Column is entitled <hi>Varia.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116062:14"/>
               <p>Thirteenthly, <hi>The unhappy juncture of a ſilly, raſh, inconſiderate Emperour; And a cunning, ſubtile, auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Pope, at the very ſame time. I mean</hi> Henry <hi>the fourth, and</hi> Pope <hi>Hildebrand alias</hi> Gregory <hi>the ſeventh. Henry</hi> led a moſt diſſolute, extravagant life, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king traffick with the <hi>German Biſhops</hi> ſelling their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments for mony. Beſides he went about to enſlave the <hi>Saxons,</hi> a conſiderable body of his ſubjects; by building Caſtles in their Country to keep them in awe, whil'ſt they were trampled upon by his licentious creatures. This made the <hi>Saxons,</hi> take armes in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe of their own liberty, and at firſt they forced him to a compoſition: But afterwards he gathering a great army together, quite routed the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a while got their chiefe Princes into his power, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt paſſed his word for their ſecurity by the mouths of his Ambaſſadours. Now ſuch was the baſeneſſe of his nature, that having once got them into his power, he brake his word and promiſe with them all, excepting <hi>Otho Duke of Bavaria,</hi> to the great regret of the <hi>German Princes.</hi> Things ſtood in this poſture, when <hi>Hildebrand or Gregory the ſeventh</hi> took occaſion to fiſh in troubled waters. For the <hi>Pope</hi> obſerving, that the <hi>Germans</hi> were generally diſcontented, with the perfidious cruelty of their Emperour, judged it the moſt opportune ſeaſon, to trample upon Emperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. Wherefore he ſummons <hi>Henry</hi> to appear at <hi>Rome,</hi> and give in his anſwers to thoſe accuſations, that were brought againſt him for ſelling the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal preferments. <hi>Henry,</hi> inſtead of appearing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116062:15"/>a Councel at <hi>Wormes.</hi> Where it is decreed, that the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhall be degraded from his pontificial dignity, becauſe he came to it by ſiniſter and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes. <hi>Hildebrand</hi> hearing this, excommunicates the chiefe of the Councel, and not only them, but the Emperour too; interdicting him from Government, and diſengaging (forſooth) his Subjects from their oath of obedience. Now one would have thought, that the world ſhould have whooted at the arrogance of this proud Prieſt, and have taken him down from that domineering throne; whence he had taken the boldneſſe to act ſuch a part of Lordly pride. But alas the <hi>Germans</hi> were ſo far from checking the Papal inſolence, as that they were glad of an occaſion to oppoſe the Emperour, for the relieving their own grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances. Wherefore they combin'd together, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuch a formidable ſtrength, that the Emperour was forced unto baſe ſubmiſſions to the Pope. And though at laſt <hi>Henry</hi> did ſo beſtir himſelfe, that he depos'd this pragmatical <hi>Gregory the ſeventh.</hi> Yet was not that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, no nor the bloud of a thouſand <hi>Hildebrands,</hi> able to waſh off that ſtain, which the Emperial Majeſty had received. For the ſucceding Popes having once had a preſident caſe, wherein they ſaw an Emperour was not only excommunicated, and interdicted from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by a Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but was forc'd to ſtoop, and ſubmit unto that interdictment, by his own ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; They never leſt afterward, to thunder out their Bulls of excommunication, againſt any Prince, that did but enterfere with their ambition.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116062:15"/>
               <p>Fourteenthly, <hi>The ſelling of the Emperial right to many chiefe Italian Cities; ſuch as Florence, Genoa, Lucca, Bologne and others, by the Emperour Rodolph of Hasburg.</hi> Who was of ſuch a careleſſe humour, as that he was wont in ſport, to give the ſame reaſon for his not viſiting <hi>Italy,</hi> which the Fox did for his not Viſiting the Lion. <hi>To wit he could ſee the ſteps of thoſe, that went thither; but not of thoſe that came back again.</hi> The truth is, <hi>Rodolph</hi>'s ſupine negligence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Italian</hi> affairs, did ſo break the neck of the Emperial intereſt in <hi>Italy,</hi> that it could never hold up it's head again to any purpoſe. For although the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Henry the ſeventh,</hi> did beſtir himſelfe ſomewhat in the ſetling of <hi>Lombardy,</hi> and appointing a <hi>Sherif</hi> to governe <hi>Milaine:</hi> yet not long after, the Emperour was grown ſo contemptible, that <hi>Charles the fourth</hi> was crowned, by the conſent of <hi>Pope Innocent the fourth,</hi> upon this condition; that he ſhould pack immediatly out of <hi>Italy. Charles</hi> obeyed his high and mighty ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and paſſing homeward through <hi>Milaine;</hi> he did utterly evacuate the Emperial power in <hi>Italy,</hi> by making the ſhreifdome of <hi>Milaine</hi> Haereditary, for which he received a good ſum of mony. A good ſum alſo his Son <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> did afterwards receive, to make the Sheriſdome a Dukedome. Thus the <hi>Popes</hi> ſaw at laſt, that which their hearts had ſo long panted after, namely the Emperours quite ſtript of their dominion in <hi>Italy,</hi> and themſelves free from being under the noſe of them, who rais'd the pontificial greatneſſe, and are by right the Lords and Maſters of their Holineſſes.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116062:16"/>After this the Emperours enjoyed, only an inſignificant titular paramountſhip over <hi>Italy;</hi> whereby they did now and then for mony, turne an Earldome into a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſate, and a Marquiſate into a Dukedome.</p>
               <p>Fifteenthly; <hi>The growing in faſhion, of a very cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ad adulterate kind of Learning, called School Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> A thing compounded of ſome truths ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal inventions, and ſome Ariſtotelical ſhall I ſay, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arabian Philoſophy. For it is certain, that the Philoſophy which then flouriſht, was taught and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by ſuch men, who underſtood not <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> Nay which is worſe, who derived their knowledg from the <hi>Arabians,</hi> that did not underſtand him themſelves. But that which made this Philoſophy the more imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect was; The men who profeſſed it were ſuch as ſate in their ſtudies, abſtracted from the obſervation and experience of things; converſing only with notions, and multiplying one notion after another, till at laſt they arrived, (pardon an odde phraſe) to the <hi>Cobweb ſubtilty of a wordy nothingneſſe.</hi> Hence it became a meer ſhop of controverſial uncertainties, and a ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of twofac'd diſtinctions, which ſerve to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance what ſide of the queſtion you pleaſe. Since therefore this Philoſophy, is of a nature ſo aequivocal, and jugling; no man needs to wonder, if the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men by applying it to Divinity, were able to faſhion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion into what forme they pleas'd. For although the whole Maſſe of their diſtinctions, could never by min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the matter, turne one falſchood into a truth: yet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116062:16"/>they might ſo far pare and ſlice a falſhood; as to make it ſhew trim enough, to deceive a praepoſſeſſed under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. I ſay a praepoſſeſſed underſtanding; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Pontificial Doctrine had in thoſe daies, taken poſſeſſion of almoſt all our parts of the Chriſtian world, and had the wealth of the nations in it's own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſal: Children were brought up in that perſwaſion, and when they were grown men, the hopes of all their preferment lay that way. Now this is palpable enough, that when the bent of our underſtanding, is enclined to any party, by the ſtrong biaſſes of education and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; We ſtraightway greedily 'embrace, all ſhewes and appearances of reaſon, which ſeem to make for our ſide; and with abundance of ſelfe applauſe, improve a meer ſneaking hint of an opinion, into a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive confidence.</p>
               <p>Sixteenthly; <hi>The thriving of the Canon Law a ſiſter profeſſion with School-Divinity.</hi> Theſe two being as it were twins borne of their Mother the <hi>Roman</hi> Church much about the ſame time, by the midwifery of <hi>Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the Monk, and <hi>Peter Lombard.</hi> As for the Canon Law, I ſuppoſe it may not unfitly be called, a meſſe of Divinity and Civil Law boild together, but burnt too, by reaſon that as we ſay in Engliſh, <hi>the Biſhop's foot have been in it,</hi> namely the foot of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Whoſoever looks into it, he may eaſily perceive, how Papal politick tenents have been forſted in as lawes. But if any one be loath to take the paines himſelfe, he ſhall find many places to this purpoſe, cited for his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116062:17"/>hand, in <hi>Sleidan's</hi> third book <hi>de quatuor ſummis impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis.</hi> Where that Judicious Authour expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, with much indignation, againſt this kind of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Nor was he alone moved with a prejudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; Many thouſands beſides him, having high reſentments of thoſe many ills, which ſpread abroad the world, by reaſon of the Canon law. Otherwiſe the <hi>Decretals</hi> would never have been branded with a proverbial ignominy, as they were in <hi>France:</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that notable tetraſtique, recorded by <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> in his Commentary on the preface of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Des puis que decret ha prins ales,</l>
                  <l>Et les Gendarmes portent males,</l>
                  <l>Et les moines vont a cheval,</l>
                  <l>En tout le mond n' ha que mal.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The firſt and laſt of theſe verſes, which only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern my purpoſe, may be thus Engliſhed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>After Decretals followed the decree,</l>
                  <l>Since that, the world hath n'ought but knavery.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Now if <hi>Gregory the ninth's decretals,</hi> were juſtly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſuch a cenſure, what ſhall we ſay of the ſixth book put out by <hi>Boniface the Eighth,</hi> of the <hi>Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116062:17"/>by <hi>Clement the fifth,</hi> and the <hi>extravagants</hi> by <hi>John the twenty ſecond?</hi> The latter Pope ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the former in arrogancy and inſolence. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever let the Canon Law be what it will; This is certain, it hath been one of the notableſt engines in the whole world, to raiſe the Papal <hi>See</hi> to an ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red heighth. For by this means the minds of many thouſands, were trained up in a reverence to the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops, who ſeem to emulate Emperial Majeſty, by taking upon them to give lawes unto the world. Now the names of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Tribonian</hi> began to dwindle, and <hi>Gregory</hi> with his <hi>Raymund</hi> grew in requeſt, nor hath ever <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> nor <hi>Galen,</hi> nor <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> nor the very <hi>Bible</hi> it ſelfe been more zealouſly ſmothered with commentatours, than the <hi>decretals</hi> of <hi>Gregory</hi> have been. Nay what ſay ye if the <hi>Canoniſts</hi> have been paſt all ſhame, in the heat of contending for their own facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? <hi>Charles du Moulin,</hi> in his Treatiſe of the <hi>French Monarchy</hi> ſaith, that ſome of them carp't at the Civil Lawes as impious and of no worth. And <hi>Francis Hottoman</hi> in his Tract intitled <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Brutum</hi> teſtifies, that they look upon the Pope as their <hi>Jupiter,</hi> giving him halves with the Emperour in the Government of the world; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by this verſe which they commonly applied to the Pope.</p>
               <q>Diviſum imperium cum Jove Caeſar habet.</q>
               <p>This is high language you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay, but perhaps it may be accounted modeſt, if we conſider how
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116062:18"/>their own law teacheth them, that the Pope is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Emperour. Wherefore no man needs to doubt, that the prevailing of ſuch a profeſſion in the world, hath been an incredible advantage to the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, as being the founder and patron thereof: For we all know, with what ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſſe of ſpirit, the profeſſours of any faculty, doe uſually contend for their patrons. Whence I may lawfully conclude, that as long as this pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial law, ſhall be attended with wealthy prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; So long the Pope will never want <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> I mean <hi>Canoniſts;</hi> Who for the ſake of their own profeſſion, and the bread which they get by it, will allwaies be ſure, to be truſty <hi>Myrmidons</hi> in the Roman cauſe.</p>
               <p>Thus have I at laſt traced out the Papal encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, through Sixteene ſeveral cauſes, without mentioning others, which ſeeme not to here ſo great and neceſſary an influence. Such as the title of <hi>Univerſal Biſhop,</hi> given unto <hi>Boniface the third,</hi> by the Tyrant <hi>Phocas.</hi> The Holy Warre, trumpeted forth by <hi>Peter the Hermite,</hi> at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of <hi>Urban the Second.</hi> The abrogation of the <hi>Roman Banderenſian</hi> Magiſtracy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Clement the Fifth,</hi> became abſolute Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the like. Far leſſe was it my intent; to take notice of <hi>Conſtantine's donation,</hi> and ſuch other things; which indeed make much for the pontificial advancement if true: But their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116062:18"/>truth is queſtioned by all indifferent men. There being as great a certainty, that many falſe ſtories have been coyn'd, as well as true ones ſuppreſſed by the Pope's creatures. Amongſt which kind of delinquents, 'tis probable that <hi>Pandulphus,</hi> the Librarian of the Lateran Church, was not the leaſt guilty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116062:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> A Corollary deduced from the preceeding diſcourſe, with a Concluſion intimating how much the Pope is beholding to the want of able and Faithfull Hiſtorians.</head>
               <p>ANd now let the Papiſts object if they pleaſe, that we have have forſaken the paths of our forefathers, with little regard unto ancient times, I pray; What is the Autiquity they boaſt of? Or what were thoſe anceſtours they upbraid us with? Can they date their Hierarchichal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, under one ſupreme head, higher than the barbarous times? And are not we, as alſo the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions round about us, the off-ſpring of Barbarians? As long as the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire ſtood firme, and the ſtock of primitive Chriſtians did remaine, there was no Pope to be heard of. Nor is it likely, that ever the progeny of thoſe men, who were converted by the Apoſtles, and taught by the Fathers, would have given way to Papal Dominion, any more than the poſterity of the <hi>Graecians</hi> did. But in come our anceſtors, a barbarous generation, halfe ſtarved with the cold of their own Climates, and reſolved for a warmer habitation. In come they, and like a deluge
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116062:19"/>carry all before them, implanting their ſelves in the roome of thoſe who were the race of firſt borne Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Which when they had done, they did with admiration here from their conquered enemies, the newes of an <hi>Omnipotent God,</hi> a <hi>Crucified Saviour,</hi> a <hi>Heaven</hi> and a <hi>Hell.</hi> Now what could be expected from theſe ignorant Barbarians, whoſe former ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was of no ſublimer ſtraine, than to worſhip <hi>the Image of a dead man, a peice of wood,</hi> or <hi>a rotten clout:</hi> Nay whoſe later diſcoveries, were made unto them by word of mouth, and taken upon truſt; they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being void of all kind of Learning, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might have been enabled to ſearch the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers? I ſay what could be expected from ſuch men, but that they ſhould be eaſily cozened; partly with the ſpecious pretenſe, of a derived ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion and ſupremacy from <hi>Peter,</hi> by the <hi>Roman</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; and partly with the colluſion between the Biſhops of that Emperial City, and their own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders.</p>
               <p>Well then; if they be deluded muſt we be ſo to? Or rather ought we not to aſſert our own liberty, and ſhake off that pontificial yoke, under which the ſpirits of our forefathers did groan? The revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of eternal providence, have brought better times upon us their Children; than ever they enjoyed. It was much about two hundred yeares agoe, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great Turke did take <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to the utter ſubverſion of the Graecian Empire. Whereby overcaſting the Sun of Chriſtianity with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116062:20"/>a diſmal cloud in the Eaſtern parts, he was the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental occaſion, that it ſhone the more bright in the Weſt. For the poore Greeks, being diſperſed all abroad; Their Learned men, to wit <hi>Theodore Gaza, John Laſcaris, Manuel Chryſaloras</hi> and others, did betake themſelves to the teaching of the Greeke tongue. Hereupon that treaſury of all arts and ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences being ſo happily retrerv'd, the purity of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning began to revive again: And thoſe books which ever ſince the daies of the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Lombards,</hi> had lain rotting in the publique libraries, were every where pulled out of heaps of duſt, and recovered from the moths and worms. By this means, we who are the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt nephewes of our barbarous anceſtours, doe yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlook them, even in reference to their own daies. and plainly perceive, that they were Heatheniſh half-witted Chriſtians for a long time, void of all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and receiving their inſtructions, from the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved policy of corrupted men. We on the contrary enjoy the Original Scriptures, and the Learned Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the primitive Chriſtians: by which it is eaſy to underſtand; that Chriſtianity is no Carnal profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion, much leſſe that on it is entayl'd the dominion of this preſent world. That the Biſhops of Rome, as well as other Biſhops their brethren, were for the firſt three hundred yeares, perſecuted by Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; And did afterwards remain in ſubjection to them, when turned Chriſtians. That it was the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous ignorance of our Anceſtors, which gave way to the Pope's eccleſiaſtique ſupremacy, and conſequently
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116062:20"/>to his temporal encroachments. Wherefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it rational, to avoid the barbariſme of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers; and to write after the Copy of thoſe men, who were the founders of our religion, and thoſe who were its firſt and pureſt profeſſours: Humbly cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving leave, to be no longer fool'd, by offering up the wealth of our Nation, and the ſweat of our Countrymens browes, in ſacrifice to a three cround Idol.</p>
               <p>And truly as often as I think, at what vaſt expence of treaſure, our Nation formerly was, and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to this day are, upon the account of their ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the <hi>Roman See:</hi> I cannot chooſe but admire a certain fatality of Dominion allwaies attending that proud City founded by <hi>Romulus.</hi> In the daies of her <hi>Senate,</hi> and alſo of her <hi>Caeſars,</hi> ſhe ſate crowned Queen amongſt the Cities, and empereſſe over the Nations, from whom ſhe received homage and tribute. When her enemies came bluſtering out of the north, more furiouſly than the winds come thence; She ſeemed indeed for a while, to hang down her head, to lean ſadly on her elbow, and to bewaile the loſſe of her former Majeſty: That Majeſty, with which ſhe commanded the Northern people, to keep beyond the <hi>Rhine</hi> and the <hi>Danow,</hi> the <hi>Parthians</hi> not to paſſe over <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and the more Southern <hi>African</hi> to ſculke behind the monntaine <hi>Atlas.</hi> But it was not long firſt, ere ſhe threw off her mourning weeds, and cloathed her ſelfe again with ſcarlet. For by the exaltation of her Biſhop, ſhe quickly obtain'd, and doth now enjoy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116062:21"/>a far larger Empire, than ever ſhe before had, even in the moſt Auguſt times of her victorious <hi>Caeſars.</hi> Do not the <hi>French, Germans,</hi> and <hi>Poles,</hi> offer up their tributary Devotions at her ſhrine? Not to mention that huge tract of ground, all along the <hi>African</hi> ſhore: Nor the Empire of <hi>Pretious or Preſtor John, or Preſtegan,</hi> call him what you will. Not to mention the <hi>Eaſt Indie Iſlands,</hi> and the vaſt continent of <hi>China,</hi> into all which places the reverence of her name hath been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; either by the <hi>Portingals,</hi> or by the miſſionary Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Doe not the Countries under the <hi>Caſtilian King,</hi> both in this and the new found world, alone aggran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize her modern Empire, beyond its greatneſſe in the dayes of old? Let no man therefore henceforward, caſt it in the <hi>Italian's</hi> teeth, as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> did; that he counts all other people barbarous. 'Tis true, the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> are the very dregs and reliques, of <hi>Goths, Vandals, Huns, Heruls, Alans, Gepids,</hi> and <hi>Lombards:</hi> yet they impute barbariſme to all other Nations, as if whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was Polite and Civil, lay circumſcribed within the narrow bounds, of the <hi>Alps,</hi> the <hi>Tyrrhene,</hi> and the <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atique</hi> Seas; as if nothing forſooth but barbarity was tramontane. But, would you know the reaſon? why? it is becauſe they have outwitted the Nations round about them, as much as ever the old <hi>Romans</hi> did the Barbarians. And what they loſt by the ſword, they have with advantage regain'd by their wit. Which he well underſtood who ſaid, <hi>Roma Caput Mundi, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid non poſſidet armis, Relligione tenet.</hi> But God be thanked, our own Nation with ſome others, have pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116062:21"/>well quitted themſelves of this barbariſme: And O when will the time come, that the reſt alſo will doe the like?</p>
               <p>When will the world rouſe up her ſelfe, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from a ſlaviſh proſtration, to the ſhallowneſſe of ſome mens notions: that great and noble ſoules may at length have a free entercourſe, or traffick for conceptions, to improve the ſtock of humane know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg? As for thoſe men who ſtill call upon us, to humble our underſtandings unto their traditions, and to deny our ſelves in our own reaſons: I wiſh they would once conſider, how ſmall the tradition concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Apoſtolical times was, when <hi>Euſebius</hi> lived. He complains in the praeface to his Hiſtory, of the ſcarce knowledg which they had in his daies, concerning the primitive Chriſtian affairs. What then muſt we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to have, who receive our information from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours ſince him? For my part, when I reflect on the ages that are gone and paſt, and the Hiſtories that are recorded of them, I cannot chuſe but deplore the partiality and weakneſſe of Eccleſiaſtique Hiſtorians: who, if we will not diſſemble, muſt needs be confeſſed, to have given lame narrations of things, and to abound with an infinite number, of impertinent, ridiculous, incredible ſtories. Inſomuch that I am very confident, we have a farre more genuine and ſincere account of thoſe times, when <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> lived; than of thoſe, when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> raigned and <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maigne.</hi> The truth is, after the barbarous inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Learning did ſo generally decay, that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116062:22"/>for a long time, either had no writers at all; or elſe ſuch, as it had been as good to have none. Otherwiſe, why did they (out of envy or ignorance or both) bury in a profound ſilence, the glorious proceedings, of that thrice renowned <hi>Saracenical</hi> Empire. An Empire of as wonderfull a growth, and as noble actions, as ever any ſince the Creation: yer we might have pardoned their foule play with the <hi>Saracens,</hi> had they been free and candid, in their relation concerning the Chriſtian affairs. Shall I tell yee? In thoſe daies, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world was overſpread, with an idle and ignorant ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of <hi>Moncks:</hi> who lay in their cels, and coyned whole legends of miraculous lies, wherewith to cheat the common people. Or elſe they were obſerving the weather, and making pretty little times, upon the ſeveral ſeaſons and tides of the yeare. But had there been any amongſt them, both able and willing, to leave unto poſterity, a full and impartial account of affairs; the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> would long before this, have been ſhamed out of their deluſory pranks. Nor ſhould I have needed to write this treatiſe, concerning the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Uſurpations.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:116062:22"/>
            <head>The Method and Contents.</head>
            <p>The Scope and Deſign of this Book is <hi>to manifeſt the Papal Uſurpation,</hi> by reflecting on Hiſtorical paſſages; and not by Logical Arguments drawn, either from Texts of Scripture, or Teſtimonies of other Authours:</p>
            <p>This <hi>manifeſtation</hi> is endeavoured two waies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> By ſhewing, that in the primitive times, the Biſhop of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> made no noiſe in the world, nor was his ſupremacy at all d'camt of. <hi>In the Firſt Chapter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> And chiefly, by ſhewing: After what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the Pope not only arrived to a Supremacy in the Church; <hi>In the Second Chapter:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alſo confirmed himſelfe, in His Eccleſiaſtical Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation; and further encroacht upon the Temporal Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. <hi>In the Third Chapter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly, In the fourth Chapter;</hi> A Corollary is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from the preceeding diſcourſe, concluding with a reaſon; Why the Pontificial unjuſt actions, have not been juſtly diſcovered.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
